Guide to the Richard Powell Papers, 1960-2011 RL.01043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Printed Materials, 1980-2011, 9 boxes
  - Exhibitions
    - LOG (Box 34)
      Includes information on Juan Logan
    - LOV-LY (Box 35)
    - MA-MAR (Box 35)
    - MAS-MC (Box 35)
      Includes information on Beverly McIver
    - ME-MI (Box 35)
    - MO-MU (Box 35)
    - N (Box 35)
    - O (Box 35)
    - PA (Box 35)
    - PE-PH (Box 35)
    - PI (Box 36)
      Includes information on Adrian Piper
    - PO (Box 36)
    - PR-PU (Box 36)
      Includes information on Vernon Pratt and Martin Puryear
    - RA (Box 36)
      Includes information on Archie Rand
    - RE (Box 36)
    - RI (Box 36)
      Includes information on Faith Ringold
    - RO (Box 36)
    - SAA (Box 36)
      Includes information on Betye Saar
    - SAL-SAR (Box 37)
    - SAU (Box 37)
      Includes information on Raymond Saunders
    - SC (Box 37)
      Includes information on Addison Scurlock
    - SE (Box 37)
    - SH-SI (Box 37)
    - SK-SM (Box 37)
      Includes information on George Smith and Vincent Smith
    - SO-SP (Box 37)
    - ST (Box 37)
    - SW-SY (Box 37)
    - TE-TH (Box 37)
      Includes information on Alma Thomas and Bob Thompson
    - TO-TW (Box 37)
    - U (Box 37)
    - V (Box 37)
    - WA (Box 37)
    - WE-WH (Box 37)
    - WI-WO (Box 37)
    - Oversize A-M (Box 60)
      Includes materials on Charles Alston, Dana, Chandler, Beauford Delaney, Mildred Howard, & "In the Spirit of Martin"
  - Periodicals, 1980-2011
    This subseries contains various publications, newspapers, and periodicals such as Art Papers, Issue, Autograph, and Tamarind, among numerous others.
    Contents are organized by title.
    - Oversize: A (Box 60)
    - Oversize B-H (Box 60)
    - Oversize R-W (Box 60)
    - AF-AL (Box 39)
      Includes Afro-American Art History Newsletter
    - ART-ARTI (Box 39)
      Includes Art and Artists and Artibus et Historiae
    - ARTM-AU (Box 39)
      Includes ArtRage and Autograph
    - B (Box 39)
      Includes Black American Literature Forum and Black Expression, among others
    - D-F (Box 39)
    - G-I (Box 39)
      Includes Issue, among others
    - J-M (Box 39)
    - N-P (Box 39)
    - R-S (Box 39)
    - T-V (Box 40)
  - Posters
    The Posters subseries contains numerous posters for museum exhibitions, talks and lectures, and other miscellaneous people and events. Also includes a small amount of miscellaneous printed materials.
    - Museum Exhibitions (Box 50-51)
    - Talks, Conferences, Lectures (Box 51)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 51, Oversize-folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 55)
    - Posters: Museum Exhibitions (Box 55)
    - Harper's Weekly Pages (Box 55)
      Text and prints: January 3, 1874, August 12, 1876, and September 7, 1878
    - The Art of Revolution: Castro's Cuba -1959-1970 (Box 56)
      Book by Dugald Stermer with an Introduction by Susan Sontag
    - WPA Document: Celebrating More than a Decade (Box 56)
      Washington Project for the Arts publication (1986)
    - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 56)
      Includes "Black Artists in America" publication, sheets of music "Boogie Woogies," and a commemorative bag from the 1986 U.S. Olympic Committee, among other items.
- Book Materials, 2000-2008, 4 boxes
  This series contains material used in the research, writing, and publication of Powell's books, particularly Cutting a Figure: Fashioning Black Portraiture(2008), Homecoming: The Art and Life of William H. Johnson, and Black Art & Culture in the 20th Century (1997).
  Material related to each publication is grouped together by the publication's title in a separate subseries.
  - Cutting a Figure: Fashioning Black Portraiture, 2000-2008 (Box 20)
    The Cutting a Figure: Fashioning Black Portraiture subseries includes correspondence with various scholars and the publisher, University of Chicago Press; the author's preparatory notes; and research material, including fashion and lifestyle periodicals, scholarly texts, newspaper articles, publications, and images. Several versions of the manuscript are also included, and represent different stages of the editing process. Additional material from this book can be found in the Donyale Luna Project Series, as detailed below.
    Folders are arranged according to the type of documents contained: research materials, publicity, manuscript copies, etc.
    - Publicity Materials (Box 20)
      University of Chicago Press publicity materials and brief review in Duke Magazine
    - Notes (Box 20)
      Preparatory notes for manuscript
    - Copyright Permission Information (Box 20)
      Correspondence, declarations, and permissions for use of copyrighted images
    - Research Materials: Texts (Box 20)
      Texts, newspaper articles, and other printed reference materials.
    - Research Materials: Images (Box 21)
      Postcards, gallery publicity, xerox-ed images, photographs, and other reference materials.
    - Correspondence: General (Box 21)
      Correspondence related to research, writing, and publication of the book.
    - Correspondence: University of California Press (Box 21)
      Correspondence about contracts and editing with the book's publisher.
    - Manuscript Copies (Box 21)
      Copies of manuscript throughout various stages of editing, Illustration List
    - Research Materials: Periodicals (Box 22)
      Periodicals used for research (including Vogue, Ebony, Life, Queen, etc.)
    - Research Materials: Periodicals (Box 23)
  - Homecoming: The Art and Life of William H. Johnson, 1984-1992
    The Homecoming: The Art and Life of William H. Johnson subseries contains extensive material Powell created and compiled in the course of researching and writing about African American artist William H. Johnson for his doctoral dissertation, Fulbright fellowship in Denmark, book, and exhibition at the Smithsonian National Museum of American Art. These materials include notebooks, a list of contacts in Scandinavia, and various printed texts pertaining to William H. Johnson written by Powell and other scholars. There is correspondence regarding a legal claim made by Johnson's family, publicity materials for the exhibition and numerous reviews in both American and Scandinavian newspapers and magazines, and extensive images. This latter group is further subdivided into two section organized by subject or theme. The first group contains images that chronicle the life of William H. Johnson, such as portraits, group images, and photographs at gallery openings, and the second section documents Johnson's artwork.
    Folders are grouped broadly by type of material or subject. Photographs are organized by either life documentation or works of art.
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (3x5 b/w photographs) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of the artist and his work
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Group Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of groups
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Gallery Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of the artist and his family in gallery spaces.
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Photographs of the Artist: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of the artist
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Portrait Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w portrait photographs
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (France & North Africa Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of people and scenes in France and North Africa
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Text Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of text, plaques, and articles
    - Life Documentation: William H. Johnson (Misc. Photographs: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of various people and works of art
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs: 3x5, color) (Box 24)
      Color photographs of William H. Johnson's works of art
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Music & Dancing: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of works of art depicting music and dancing
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Landscapes: 8x10 b/w and color) (Box 24)
      B/w and color photographs of works of art depicting landscapes
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Religious Works: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of works of art with religious subjects
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Misc. Works: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of various works of art: still lifes, texts, etc.
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Military Works: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of works of art with military themes
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Historical Works: 8x10 b/w) (Box 24)
      B/w photographs of works of art with historical themes
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Outdoor Scenes: 8x10 b/w) (Box 25)
      B/w photographs of works featuring farmyard or outdoor scenes
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, People: 8x10 b/w) (Box 25)
      B/w photographs of works featuring couples and groups
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Photographs, Portraits: 8x10 b/w and color) (Box 25)
      B/w and color photographs of portraits
    - Notebooks (Box 42)
      Includes one notebook on contacts for the project throughout Europe and two with extensive handwritten notes
    - Diggs Gallery (Box 43)
      Information from an exhibition on Johnson
    - WETA/National Endowment for the Arts (Box 43)
      Includes application and correspondence
    - Correspondence (Box 43)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 43)
    - WHJ Lecture (Box 43)
    - Notes (Box 43)
      Research Notes
    - Research Materials (Box 43)
      Reproductions of documents pertaining to the life of William H. Johnson including medical forms, letters, etc. and other related artists
    - Works of Art: William H. Johnson (Misc. Works) (Box 43)
      Reproductions of works of art, b/w and color, various sizes
    - Essays (Box 44)
      Texts about William H. Johnson by Dr. Powell and others
    - Legal Documents (Box 44)
      Correspondence pertaining to a legal case about ownership of works by William H. Johnson
    - Exhibition Publicity: Smithsonian NMAA (Box 44)
    - Exhibition Publicity: Other Museums (Box 44)
      Publicity for the exhibition at other institutions including the Florence Museum of Art, Science and History and the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art at Cornell, among others
    - Exhibition Publicity: Newspapers (Box 44)
      Includes various articles on the exhibition in English.
    - Exhibition Publicity: Scandinavian Newspapers (Box 44)
      Includes various articles on the exhibition in Scandinavian newspapers.
    - Book Contract (Box 44)
      Correspondence regarding to Dr. Powell's book contract for the project.
  - Black Art & Culture in the 20th Century, 1990-1998
    This subseries contains research materials and correspondence relating to Powell's 1997 book, Black Art & Culture in the 20th Century. Materials include press releases and reviews of the book, publicity materials, such as a book signing, and extensive correspondence with the book's publisher, Thames & Hudson Limited, concerning the editing and publication of Black Art & Culture. There is also a limited amount of research notes and reference materials.
    Folders are arranged by type of material.
    - Publicity Materials (Box 26)
      Press Releases, Reviews, Articles on Dr. Powell's book
    - Research Materials (Box 26)
      Newspaper Articles, Texts, and other reference materials
    - Correspondence (Box 26)
      Correspondence with publisher Thames and Hudson Ltd.
    - Research Notes & Permissions (Box 26)
      Research notes and image copyright permission information
- Reference Images Series, 1984-2011, 1 box
  This series includes reference images in a variety of formats, most commonly photographs, transparencies, prints, postcards, and photocopies.
  The images are organized by size, medium, or subject.
  - Small Format (color) (Box 25)
    Small size color reproductions of various works of art
  - Small Format (b/w) (Box 25)
    Small size b/w reproductions of various works of art
  - Large Format, Paginated (Box 25)
    Various works of art with annotations and page numbers attached
  - African Art (Photographs) (Box 25)
    B/w photographs of African works of art
  - National Humanities Center Prints (Box 25)
    Various works of art on plates produced by the National Humanities Center 2003 Summer Institute
  - Photographs of Works on Paper (Box 25)
    Photographs of various works of drawings, paintings, and prints
  - Sculpture, Collage, & 3D Works (Photographs) (Box 25)
    Photographs and reproductions of various three-dimensional works of art
  - Reproductions of Photographs (Box 26)
    Reproductions of various b/w photographs
  - Advertisements & Images with Text (Box 26)
    Various advertisements and printed images with accompanying text
  - Postcards (Box 29)
    Reproductions of various works of art
  - Large Postcards (Box 29)
  - Large Format Reproductions (Box 30)
  - Postcard Book (Box 30)
    "Los Angeles Murals by African-American Artists"
- Exhibitions, 1989-2010, 4 boxes
  The Exhibitions Series contains information on various museum exhibitions and catalogues on which Powell worked throughout his career. The files in this series include correspondence and reviews as well as research notes and, in many cases, extensive publicity materials such as pamphlets, press kits, and flyers.
  The series is grouped into several subseries by exhibition title or subject.
  - Exhibition: Back to Black, 2000-2005
    Back to Black: Art, Cinema and the Racial Imaginary opened at London's Whitechapel Art Gallery in 2005. Dr. Powell participated as a curator and catalogue contributor. The materials in this subseries include notes, emails, and reference texts pertaining to the exhibition.
    - Correspondence & Research Materials (Box 26)
      Emails, notes, texts concerning Back to Black: Art, Cinema and the Racial Imaginary exhibition at London's Whitechapel Art Gallery, 2005
  - Exhibition: To Conserve a Legacy, 1997-1999
    The 1999 exhibition To Conserve a Legacy: American Art from Historically Black Colleges and Universities was shown at the Studio Museum in Harlem, NY, The Art Institute of Chicago, and the Addison Gallery of American Art, Andover, MA. The materials include newspaper and magazine reviews, planning and organizational resources, and correspondence regarding the exhibition. There are also extensive publicity materials, including exhibition cards, a press kit, and press releases.
    - Correspondence (Box 26)
      Correspondence relating to the exhibition To Conserve a Legacy: American Art from Historically Black Colleges and Universities
    - Reviews (Box 27)
      Newspaper articles
    - Planning Materials (Box 27)
      Corporate and foundation letters of support, project description, information for internships, meetings, and the symposium
    - Publicity Materials (Box 27)
      Press kit, exhibition cards, press releases, and other materials publicizing the exhibition
  - Exhibition: Circle Dance, 2003-2005
    Includes materials related to the 2005 exhibition Circle Dance: The Art of John T. Scott at the New Orleans Museum of Art, for which Dr. Powell as both a curator and catalogue author. This subseries contains correspondence, including a letter on hand-made paper from John T. Scott, research materials, such as newspaper articles and image lists, and publicity information and a media kit from the New Orleans Museum of Art.
    - Correspondence (Box 27)
      Emails and letters pertaining to the organization and planning of the exhibition
    - Notes & Planning Materials (Box 27)
      Image lists, John Scott's CV, research and planning notes
    - Reference Materials (Box 27)
      Internet and newspaper articles about John Scott and other related subjects, as well as slides. Includes a package of materials prepared by John Scott
    - Publicity Materials (Box 27)
      Press kit and news release for the exhibition
  - Exhibition: Barkley L. Hendricks, 2000-2008
    Research materials related to Dr. Powell's work on artist Barkley L. Hendricks. Includes material related to the 2001 exhibition at the Connecticut College Lyman Allyn Museum of Art, for which Dr. Powell contributed a catalogue entry entitled "To Be Real" (in The Barkley L. Hendricks Experience) and the 2008 exhibition Barkley L. Hendricks/Birth of the Cool at the Duke University Nasher Museum of Art. Materials include correspondence with the artist, information about the artist's other shows, and Powell's research notes.
    - Correspondence (Box 28)
      Letters and emails, including postcards and letters from the artist
    - Research Materials & Notes (Box 28)
      Artist's CV and biography, Dr. Powell's notes
    - Exhibition Materials (Box 28)
      Publicity cards for various Barkley L. Hendricks exhibitions
    - Reviews (Box 28)
      Newspaper and magazine articles reviewing various exhibitions by the artist
    - Miscellaneous Clippings (Box 28)
      Newspapers
  - Exhibition: Rhapsodies in Black, 1995-1997
    This subseries documents Powell's involvement in the 1997 exhibition Rhapsodies in Black: Art of the Harlem Renaissance, shown at the Hayward Gallery of London, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, and Washington D.C.'s Corcoran Gallery of Art, among other venues. It includes extensive publicity materials for the exhibition, such as news releases, a press kit, and newspaper and magazine reviews. It also contains a selection of photographs documenting the opening and Powell's visit to London.
    - Reviews (Box 28)
      Newspaper and magazine articles on the exhibition
    - Publicity Materials (Box 29)
      Press pack, exhibition flyers, news releases and gallery cards
    - Photographs (Box 29)
      Photographs of the exhibition's London opening
  - Exhibition: The Blues Aesthetic, 1989-1998
    This subseries contains documents related to the 1989 exhibition The Blues Aesthetic: Black Culture and Modernism, which shown was at Washington D.C.'s Washington Project for the Arts and other U.S. venues. Powell served as the curator for the exhibition and was extensively involved in the exhibition catalogue. In addition to the exhibition, he taught an undergraduate class at Duke University on the subject in Fall 1998, and planning and lecture materials for this course are included. This subseries contains newspaper clippings and articles concerning the controversial David Hammons work "How Ya Like Me Now?" which was erected and quickly destroyed during Dr. Powell's tenure as curator and acting co-director at W.P.A.
    - Research Materials & Notes (Box 29)
      Exhibition project outline, slide lists, course materials
    - Publicity Materials (Box 29)
      Pamphlets, exhibition cards, and a full press kit for the exhibition
    - Reviews (Box 29)
      Includes reviews of the exhibition as well as newspaper articles concerning the David Hammons work "How Ya Like Me Now?"
  - Exhibition: Conjuring Bearden, 2004-2006
    This subseries contains materials related to the development of the Nasher Museum's 2006 exhibition, Conjuring Bearden, which Powell curated with the assistance of students. The subseries includes an itinerary for the group's research trip to New York, publicity cards, pamphlets, and reviews of the exhibition.
    - Exhibition Proposal (Box 29)
      Proposal for the Nasher exhibition, including research materials and NYC itinerary
    - Exhibition Materials (Box 29)
      Includes images, planning meeting notes, and budget
    - Publicity Materials (Box 29)
      Reviews and articles about the exhibition
- Donyale Luna Project, 2006-2009, 1 box
  This series contains notes, documents, and other materials related to Powell's research on the African-American 1960s supermodel Donyale Luna, to whose life and portraiture Powell dedicated a chapter in his 2008 book, Cutting a Figure: Fashioning Black Portraiture. The materials include reproductions of Luna's passport applications, death certificates for both her and her father, social security information, and interviews with the model's friends and associates in Detroit, Italy, and France. An exhibition proposal for a show on Donyale Luna, including extensive high-quality photographs, and numerous newspaper articles discussing her life are also included.
  - Images (Box 28)
    Photographs and reproductions
  - Correspondence (Box 28)
    Letters, emails, and faxes pertaining to Dr. Powell's research
  - Research Materials: Articles (Box 28)
    Newspaper and magazine articles about Donyale Luna
  - Research Materials & Notes (Box 28)
    Notes and extensive documents for Donyale Luna project including death certificates, interviews, passport photocopies, etc. as well as an exhibition proposal
- Personal and Early Papers, 1960-2011, 3 boxes
  This series contains documents pertaining to Powell's childhood, collegiate and graduate education, and early years as a member of the Duke University faculty. Materials include elementary school projects, various versions of Dr. Powell's C.V. and resume, an address book, and publicity materials related to his various lectures and exhibitions.
  The series is divided into topical subsections including Elementary School, C.V.'s and Resumes, Morehouse, Yale, Duke, and Personal.
  - Elementary School (Box 40)
    Includes awards and school papers
  - C.V. and Resume Drafts with Notes (Box 40)
    Includes various iterations of Dr. Powell's CV with annotations
  - C.V. and Resume Drafts (Box 40)
    Various iterations of Dr. Powell's CV from appx. 1985-Present
  - Morehouse College and Yale (Box 40)
    Includes Fulbright report, reunion photo and honors
  - Interviews (Box 40)
    1989 WPA Interview and 1991 African American Art History Publication Interview
  - Duke University (Box 40)
    Synopsis of scholarly activities and profile, applications for Rockefeller, Ford Foundation, and National Center for the Humanities
  - Duke University Awards (Box 40)
  - Lectures & Talks (Box 40)
    Publicity for Dr. Powell's lectures and talks
  - Events (Box 40)
    Includes a menu for dinner at Bill and Melinda Gates and an invitation for dinner in Dr. Powell's honor at the National Gallery of Art
  - Art Exhibitions (Box 40)
    Publicity for exhibitions of Dr. Powell's artwork
  - Correspondence (Box 40)
    Misc. correspondence, including a letter from Dr. Powell to First Lady Michelle Obama
  - Magazine & Newspaper Articles (Box 40)
    Various articles chronicling Dr. Powell's career
  - Miscellaneous Clippings (Box 40)
  - Denmark (Box 40)
    Includes ID, transportation tickets
  - Notebooks (Box 41)
    Includes book from printmaking workshop at Norfolk College
  - Journals (Box 42)
  - Address Book (Box 42)
  - Unbound Rolodex Cards (Box 61)
- Articles and Lectures by Powell, 1975-2011, 5 boxes
  Contains materials related to various published articles, graduate research papers from Yale and Howard Universities, and lectures given by Powell. The documents included in this series are notes, research materials, handwritten and typed drafts, and published texts from throughout Powell's career. Also includes some publicity materials and correspondence pertaining to Powell's public lectures.
  Folders are arranged by article/lecture title or by type of material.
  - Miscellaneous Drafts & Notes (Box 45)
  - Correspondence (Box 45)
  - The Black World in Literature for Children (Box 45)
    Printed publication
  - "African American Postmodernism and David Hammons" (Box 45)
    Article
  - "African and Afro-American Art: Call and Response" (Box 45)